<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>podcast on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/tags/podcast/</link>
    <description>Recent content in podcast on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/podcast/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Mushtaq: Doctor to Coding Architect (Expertease Podcast #5)</title>
      <link>/2021/10/31/31-podcast-expertease-mushtaq-doctor-to-architect/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/10/31/31-podcast-expertease-mushtaq-doctor-to-architect/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Mushtaq Ahmed: From Doctor to Coding Architect - Episode #5 In this episode on Expertease, we have an honest and insightful conversation with a dear friend and colleague Mushtaq Ahmed, Principal Consultant at Thoughtworks Pune. We cover topics ranging from his interests, his journey from studying to be a Doctor, then becoming a BA, then a Developer and now a Senior Technical Leader; and his passion for programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insights on Career, Mastery and Craftsmanship (Expertease Podcast #4)</title>
      <link>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad (Part1) - Empowered Engineering Culture - Episode #3 In Part 1 of our conversation with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, we discussed ways &amp;amp; means of building an empowered Engineering culture, and how Mastery, Autonomy and Purpose play a key role in building a vibrant company culture. You can listen to the insighful conversation here: Nikhil Prasad - Part 1 - Engineering culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empowered Engineering Culture - Nikhil Prasad (Expertease Podcast #3)</title>
      <link>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad - Cultivating an Empowered Engineering Culture (Part1) In this third episode of Expertease, we have an insightful chat with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, a 700 people, product company, that is considered to be a strong people-centric organisation in Pune.
  Nikhil Prasad   Nikhil talks about&amp;hellip;
&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;If the why is ambitious &amp;amp; empowering, then it adds Purpose to the mission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exiting the Rat Race -  The Entrepreneurial Journey of Sandeep Nanu (Expertease Podcast #2)</title>
      <link>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Sandeep Nanu - Exiting the Rat Race In this second episode of Expertease, we have a spirited chat with Sandeep Nanu, serial entrepreneur and founder of a brand and communication consulting firm WriteClick.
  Sandeep Nanu   Sandeep talks about his first job as a WebDesigner and the lessons he learnt there, including the important of respecting your commitments to other and their time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art of Experience Design with Aditya Karle (Expertease Podcast #1)</title>
      <link>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Description In this first episode of Expertease, we have a light-hearted chat with Aditya Karle, Head of Design at ThoughtWorks India, to deconstruct the art of Experience Design (XD).
  Aditya Karle   1:10: We talk about his journey to becoming a Designer and getting involved in Software Design, discuss differences between UI design, UX and XD.
28:50: We have an interesting chat about applying design thinking to Bengaluru International Airport.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Open Source Software</title>
      <link>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained/</guid>
      <description>My acoustic guitar - Greg Bennett   I have been contributing to Open Source Software (OSS) for over 3 years now, at ThoughtWorks. Many people seem to have some misconceptions about OSS, or don’t fully realise the implications and impact of OSS. In this blog, I have shared a few of my learnings and thoughts on this topic. If you are technologist – who has some familiarity with OSS, then it’s likely that this article will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
