<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/tags/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I Know That I Know Nothing</title>
      <link>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox/</guid>
      <description>In this blog I introduce a model for helping us articulate unknowns in our knowledge and in projects.&#xA;Beach side in Colombo, Sri Lanka Introduction to the Model Some months ago, while attending a ThoughtWorks Leadership training program, I encountered a very fascinating awareness model (** It’s inspired from the Johari Window model. See notes at the end of the blog). I was captivated by its implications.&#xA;This is how it looks:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are You Telling A Story?</title>
      <link>/2018/03/31/art-of-story-telling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2018/03/31/art-of-story-telling/</guid>
      <description>My Martin Backpaker Guitar Student: I am giving my first talk in 6 weeks.&#xA;Teacher: Excellent.&#xA;Student: When would you call a presentation a success?&#xA;Teacher: The audience vividly remembers it 3 days after you presented it.&#xA;Student: How can I make this happen?&#xA;Teacher: By telling a compelling story, instead of stating the facts.&#xA;Student: Why is a story important?&#xA;Teacher: Imagine this. You are sitting for lunch with your team, and you suddenly remember that one of your colleagues attended the XP conference yesterday.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>12 Things I Learnt While Teaching Application Security</title>
      <link>/2017/04/12/app-security-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/04/12/app-security-learning/</guid>
      <description>Turkey (Istanbul) Introduction ThoughtWorks runs an Application Security 101 training for people not very familiar with common security topics. The training curriculum covers topics like Threat Modelling, Same Origin Policy, CSRF, Secret Management, Library Vulnerabilities, STRIDE among many others.&#xA;I was a trainer for one of the recent batches in ThoughtWorks Pune, and in researching some of these topics, I came across many interesting links, videos and information. I decided to write a blog outlining them as a reference for my &amp;lsquo;students&amp;rsquo;.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Podcasts I Love</title>
      <link>/2015/11/15/podcasts-i-love/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/11/15/podcasts-i-love/</guid>
      <description>Tibetan artists in Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India Driving in India is a test of patience. And a waste of time.&#xA;A few months ago, I decided to try an experiment while driving to office, about a 30 minute ride each way. The experiment was: Podcasts.&#xA;Turns out, I had uncovered something amazing. Podcasts made me forget the time I spend on the road, and instead opened a window to a world I didn&amp;rsquo;t know existed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Way To A New Project</title>
      <link>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project/</guid>
      <description>On top of Mt Billing in Dharamshala, India You move to a new project. Its exciting. It holds promise of something awesome (usually). You are ready to dive. You want to learn things fast. You want to contribute. You want to become effective. You want to be welcomed. And then maybe, become invaluable.&#xA;There are some tips I have learnt on how to navigate new projects effectively. I would look forward to hearing what you have to say about yours.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
