<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>career on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in career on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Insights on Career, Mastery and Craftsmanship (Expertease Podcast #4)</title>
      <link>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad (Part1) - Empowered Engineering Culture - Episode #3 In Part 1 of our conversation with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, we discussed ways &amp;amp; means of building an empowered Engineering culture, and how Mastery, Autonomy and Purpose play a key role in building a vibrant company culture. You can listen to the insighful conversation here: Nikhil Prasad - Part 1 - Engineering culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empowered Engineering Culture - Nikhil Prasad (Expertease Podcast #3)</title>
      <link>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad - Cultivating an Empowered Engineering Culture (Part1) In this third episode of Expertease, we have an insightful chat with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, a 700 people, product company, that is considered to be a strong people-centric organisation in Pune.
  Nikhil Prasad   Nikhil talks about&amp;hellip;
&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;If the why is ambitious &amp;amp; empowering, then it adds Purpose to the mission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Know That I Know Nothing</title>
      <link>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox.html/</guid>
      <description>In this blog I introduce a model for helping us articulate unknowns in our knowledge and in projects.
  Beach side in Colombo, Sri Lanka   Introduction to the Model Some months ago, while attending a ThoughtWorks Leadership training program, I encountered a very fascinating awareness model (** It’s inspired from the Johari Window model. See notes at the end of the blog). I was captivated by its implications.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
