<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/post.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Indian Food Recipes App built with GlideApps [NoCode]</title>
      <link>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode.html</guid>
      <description>Free App with over 100&amp;#43; Indian recipes   Food Recipes App - NoCode My brother (Simarpreet), who is a home-chef, wanted to create a mobile app with Indian food recipes (mostly as made in Punjabi homes). The idea being that one has an app in their pocket that can be pulled out while doing grocery shopping, or standing in the kitchen, to quickly see simple home made recipes &amp;amp; ingredients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bahmni - Open Source EMR with 1 Million Lines of Code</title>
      <link>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc.html</guid>
      <description>Image courtsey: Friends without borders   Bahmni Codebase - Moving out of AngularJS Bahmni, an open source hospital management system and EMR has over 1 Million lines of code (LoC)! Out of that over 164,000 LoC are in AngularJS (Angular 1.x). AngularJS is going to be end-of-life in Dec-2021, with no likely SLAs around fixes after Dec-2021.
In this article, I would like to shed some light into what parts of Bahmni depend on AngularJS, what parts are already in React; and suggest some steps forward to remove dependence on AngularJS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insights on Career, Mastery and Craftsmanship (Expertease Podcast #4)</title>
      <link>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad (Part1) - Empowered Engineering Culture - Episode #3 In Part 1 of our conversation with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, we discussed ways &amp;amp; means of building an empowered Engineering culture, and how Mastery, Autonomy and Purpose play a key role in building a vibrant company culture. You can listen to the insighful conversation here: Nikhil Prasad - Part 1 - Engineering culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empowered Engineering Culture - Nikhil Prasad (Expertease Podcast #3)</title>
      <link>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad - Cultivating an Empowered Engineering Culture (Part1) In this third episode of Expertease, we have an insightful chat with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, a 700 people, product company, that is considered to be a strong people-centric organisation in Pune.
  Nikhil Prasad   Nikhil talks about&amp;hellip;
&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;If the why is ambitious &amp;amp; empowering, then it adds Purpose to the mission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exiting the Rat Race -  The Entrepreneurial Journey of Sandeep Nanu (Expertease Podcast #2)</title>
      <link>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu.html</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Sandeep Nanu - Exiting the Rat Race In this second episode of Expertease, we have a spirited chat with Sandeep Nanu, serial entrepreneur and founder of a brand and communication consulting firm WriteClick.
  Sandeep Nanu   Sandeep talks about his first job as a WebDesigner and the lessons he learnt there, including the important of respecting your commitments to other and their time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art of Experience Design with Aditya Karle (Expertease Podcast #1)</title>
      <link>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design.html</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Description In this first episode of Expertease, we have a light-hearted chat with Aditya Karle, Head of Design at ThoughtWorks India, to deconstruct the art of Experience Design (XD).
  Aditya Karle   1:10: We talk about his journey to becoming a Designer and getting involved in Software Design, discuss differences between UI design, UX and XD.
28:50: We have an interesting chat about applying design thinking to Bengaluru International Airport.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 reasons for buying the Ford EcoSport Petrol (Automatic) - Review</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/ford-ecosport-automatic.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/ford-ecosport-automatic.html</guid>
      <description>I spent a few months researching automatic petrol vehicles in India, before finally settling on the Ford EcoSport. Read on to find out why.
  Ford EcoSport   Disclaimer: Car specifications and quality are always changing. Please contact respective brands and companies for current specifications. This blog is based on my research to purchase a good petrol automatic vehicle for my needs, and I do not take any liability on the accuracy of the information mentioned here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Know That I Know Nothing</title>
      <link>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/05/12/i-know-nothing-socrates-paradox.html</guid>
      <description>In this blog I introduce a model for helping us articulate unknowns in our knowledge and in projects.
  Beach side in Colombo, Sri Lanka   Introduction to the Model Some months ago, while attending a ThoughtWorks Leadership training program, I encountered a very fascinating awareness model (** It’s inspired from the Johari Window model. See notes at the end of the blog). I was captivated by its implications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are You Telling A Story?</title>
      <link>/2018/03/31/art-of-story-telling.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/03/31/art-of-story-telling.html</guid>
      <description>My Martin Backpaker Guitar   Student: I am giving my first talk in 6 weeks.
Teacher: Excellent.
Student: When would you call a presentation a success?
Teacher: The audience vividly remembers it 3 days after you presented it.
Student: How can I make this happen?
Teacher: By telling a compelling story, instead of stating the facts.
Student: Why is a story important?
Teacher: Imagine this. You are sitting for lunch with your team, and you suddenly remember that one of your colleagues attended the XP conference yesterday.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12 Things I Learnt While Teaching Application Security</title>
      <link>/2017/04/12/app-security-learning.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/12/app-security-learning.html</guid>
      <description>Turkey (Istanbul)   Introduction ThoughtWorks runs an Application Security 101 training for people not very familiar with common security topics. The training curriculum covers topics like Threat Modelling, Same Origin Policy, CSRF, Secret Management, Library Vulnerabilities, STRIDE among many others.
I was a trainer for one of the recent batches in ThoughtWorks Pune, and in researching some of these topics, I came across many interesting links, videos and information.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Open Source Software</title>
      <link>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained.html</guid>
      <description>My acoustic guitar - Greg Bennett   I have been contributing to Open Source Software (OSS) for over 3 years now, at ThoughtWorks. Many people seem to have some misconceptions about OSS, or don’t fully realise the implications and impact of OSS. In this blog, I have shared a few of my learnings and thoughts on this topic. If you are technologist – who has some familiarity with OSS, then it’s likely that this article will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduce Computer Eye Strain with F.lux</title>
      <link>/2016/09/05/reduce-eye-strain-with-flux.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/09/05/reduce-eye-strain-with-flux.html</guid>
      <description>About 3 years ago, one of my colleagues in ThoughtWorks, Sam Gibson, suggested I try out f.lux.
f.lux changes the Color temperature of my mac screen in the evening, so that the blue light from the screen is removed, and instead a nice warm set of colors are emitted from the screen. This drastically reduced the strain that I felt on my screen at night. It felt weird, the first 3 or 4 days, when my screen colors changed in the evening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mars Rover Problem in Scala</title>
      <link>/2016/04/24/mars-rover-problem-in-scala.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/24/mars-rover-problem-in-scala.html</guid>
      <description>Priyank Gupta, a respected ex-ThoughtWorker from the Pune office, wrote an excellent blog series in 2014 titled: Decoding ThoughtWorks Coding Problems.
In this blog he explains what constitutes good code &amp;amp; design, using the now decommissioned Mars Rover problem as an example. His code is in Java. I decided to showcase the same design in Scala, using only &amp;ldquo;the good parts&amp;rdquo; of Scala, with an aim of keeping the solution easy to understand, and enhance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Money gets in the way of Life</title>
      <link>/2016/03/03/money-in-way-of-life.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/03/03/money-in-way-of-life.html</guid>
      <description>Credits: Singapore Art Museum   A dialog between a Human and a Doctor goes like this in most parts of the world&amp;hellip;
I wrote this blog on Bahmni Community Blogs on Medium. Read the full blog here: When Money gets in the way of Life - Bahmni Blogs</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every Single Retro</title>
      <link>/2016/02/03/every-single-retro.html</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/02/03/every-single-retro.html</guid>
      <description>The outcome of almost every retro can be captured easily by this poster:
  Every Single Retro   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Velocity Conundrum</title>
      <link>/2015/12/25/the-velocity-conundrum.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/12/25/the-velocity-conundrum.html</guid>
      <description>Near Chinatown street in Singapore   Velocity! It&amp;rsquo;s a term that has potentially confounded, frustrated and perhaps amused Agile practitioners and customers alike at some point. It&amp;rsquo;s a concept that can be quite helpful though, when used accurately as a planning &amp;amp; estimation tool.
Velocity is a measure of the number of story points delivered in an Iteration. The word delivered here means - dev &amp;amp; test complete, and ready for Production.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcasts I Love</title>
      <link>/2015/11/15/podcasts-i-love.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/11/15/podcasts-i-love.html</guid>
      <description>Tibetan artists in Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   Driving in India is a test of patience. And a waste of time.
A few months ago, I decided to try an experiment while driving to office, about a 30 minute ride each way. The experiment was: Podcasts.
Turns out, I had uncovered something amazing. Podcasts made me forget the time I spend on the road, and instead opened a window to a world I didn&amp;rsquo;t know existed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I moved to Jekyll</title>
      <link>/2015/11/01/i-moved-to-jekyll.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/11/01/i-moved-to-jekyll.html</guid>
      <description>Tibetan artists in Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   My blog on Google Blogspot techie-notebook.blogspot.com hit the 100,000 views mark. I am super excited. But, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really like the way my blog looked. I wanted it to be simple. I wanted it to be elegant. I wanted to render code, like it should. I wanted the programmer in me, to be in control. So I moved to Jekyll.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Vagrant Boxes and VMs</title>
      <link>/2015/10/03/understanding-vagrant-boxes.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/03/understanding-vagrant-boxes.html</guid>
      <description>On top of Mt Billing in Dharamshala, India   Vagrant does a lot of things auto-magically under the hoods, and most of the times people are left confused when they want to delete or add boxes or VMs. I will try and explain the relationships between Base Boxes, VMs, Virtual Box Instances among other things, in this post.
Vagrant is an awesome tool for developers to get their own sandboxed environments to play with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server on a Digital Ocean Droplet</title>
      <link>/2015/08/16/gocd-on-digital-ocean.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/08/16/gocd-on-digital-ocean.html</guid>
      <description>Near Chinatown street in Singapore   Today I experimented with installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server and agent on a Digital Ocean CentOS droplet. Note that you will need to ensure that you setup swap space on your digital ocean droplet, before proceeding with installing GoCD.
Read the steps here on my old blog: Installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server and Agent on Digital Ocean Droplet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Applications for Multiple Countries and Languages</title>
      <link>/2015/02/14/building-apps-for-multiple-countries.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/02/14/building-apps-for-multiple-countries.html</guid>
      <description>Near Chinatown street in Singapore   I have worked on a couple of projects where we had to make the application multi-country savvy (also called internationalisation or i18n), and I think it would be good to pen down various areas we considered, and the tools we used. Note that, these practices are from the perspective of a Java/Scala project, but can easily be adapted to other platforms too &amp;ndash; since the basic requirements are similar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Way To A New Project</title>
      <link>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project.html</guid>
      <description>On top of Mt Billing in Dharamshala, India   You move to a new project. Its exciting. It holds promise of something awesome (usually). You are ready to dive. You want to learn things fast. You want to contribute. You want to become effective. You want to be welcomed. And then maybe, become invaluable.
There are some tips I have learnt on how to navigate new projects effectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Difference between sorted, sortWith and sortBy in Scala</title>
      <link>/2014/07/26/scala-diff-between-sort-methods.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/07/26/scala-diff-between-sort-methods.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   Scala collections provide you three options for sorting: sorted(), sortWith() and sortBy(). Here is a simplified explanation:
sorted Will sort the list using the natural ordering (based on the implicit Ordering passed)
sortBy (an attribute) Sort by a given attribute using the attribute&amp;rsquo;s type. e.g. given a list of Person objects, if you want to sort them in ascending order of their age (which is an Int), you could simply say:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Capybara and Rspec assertions in Page Objects</title>
      <link>/2014/01/10/using-capybara-and-rspec.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2014/01/10/using-capybara-and-rspec.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   On my Rails project, I am using RSpec and Capybara to write functional tests.
I did not want to specify any HTML elements in my Capybara feature files, since that makes the feature files brittle to HTML / CSS changes. It also violates the DRY principle and basic code hygiene.
Read the full blog on my older blog site here: Using Capybara and Rspec assertions in Page Objects</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vagrant: Setup development environments FAST!</title>
      <link>/2012/12/16/vagrant-an-interesting-approach-dev.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/12/16/vagrant-an-interesting-approach-dev.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   If you have never heard of Vagrant, or are interested in understanding what is Vagrant, then this blog should be useful to you.
Setting up a development environment for many projects now-a-days isn&amp;rsquo;t a matter of simply running a script or downloading a piece of software. On most projects, the average setup time to get all up and running is usually a day, and sometimes more.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Reading for Lateral Dev Hires at ThoughtWorks</title>
      <link>/2012/07/29/recommended-reading-for-devs-thoughtworks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/29/recommended-reading-for-devs-thoughtworks.html</guid>
      <description>ThoughtWorks Tech Radar - Times Square   Quite often experienced folks joining ThoughtWorks have a common set of questions: What should I read to prepare myself for ThoughtWorks? What kind of technologies does ThoughtWorks work on? Will I go on a Ruby or Java or Mobile project?
I doubt there is any good and precise answer to these questions. But, there certainly are some practices that I feel our in the DNA of ThoughtWorks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>POKA YOKE - Applying Mistake Proofing to Software</title>
      <link>/2012/07/22/poke-yoke-mistake-proofing-software.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/07/22/poke-yoke-mistake-proofing-software.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   Note: This has been one of my highest read blog posts ever with over 100,000 views. I am humbled. Thank you!
For years, automobile companies have utilized &amp;ldquo;Mistake Proofing&amp;rdquo; as a technique for ensuring high quality, high speed manufacturing &amp;ndash; especially in cases of mass scale production. This is also known as Poka-Yoke (in Japanese) and was adopted and formalized as part of the Toyota Production System.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Vulnerabilities - Phishing, Cookies, XSS and CSRF</title>
      <link>/2012/04/29/understanding-web-vulnerabilities-cookies.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/04/29/understanding-web-vulnerabilities-cookies.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   Last week I gave a presentation on &amp;ldquo;Web Application Vulnerabilities&amp;rdquo; as part of our weekly Dev meetup at ThoughtWorks. The presentation was aimed at covering some vulnerabilities and risks that plague Web based applications, and to make folks aware of risks and possible mitigation options. In specific, topics covered were Phishing, Social Engineering, Cookies and Cross Site Request Forgery (CSRF or XSRF).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8 months at ThoughtWorks Pune</title>
      <link>/2012/02/25/eight-months-at-tw-pune.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2012/02/25/eight-months-at-tw-pune.html</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India   I joined ThoughtWorks, Pune in June 2011. 8 months ago. Previously I had worked with Persistent Systems, IBM Software Labs and Performix (a start-up). I would like to pen down my ThoughtWorks journey so far. Correction. Incredible journey.
For sake of readability, let&amp;rsquo;s list down the things I feel are awesome and different about ThoughtWorks, and why I catch myself wondering why the hell did I not apply to ThoughtWorks earlier.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
