<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>india on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/tags/india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in india on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Indian Food Recipes App built with GlideApps [NoCode]</title>
      <link>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode.html/</guid>
      <description>Free App with over 100&amp;#43; Indian recipes   Food Recipes App - NoCode My brother (Simarpreet), who is a home-chef, wanted to create a mobile app with Indian food recipes (mostly as made in Punjabi homes). The idea being that one has an app in their pocket that can be pulled out while doing grocery shopping, or standing in the kitchen, to quickly see simple home made recipes &amp;amp; ingredients.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bahmni - Open Source EMR with 1 Million Lines of Code</title>
      <link>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc.html/</guid>
      <description>Image courtsey: Friends without borders   Bahmni Codebase - Moving out of AngularJS Bahmni, an open source hospital management system and EMR has over 1 Million lines of code (LoC)! Out of that over 164,000 LoC are in AngularJS (Angular 1.x). AngularJS is going to be end-of-life in Dec-2021, with no likely SLAs around fixes after Dec-2021.
In this article, I would like to shed some light into what parts of Bahmni depend on AngularJS, what parts are already in React; and suggest some steps forward to remove dependence on AngularJS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insights on Career, Mastery and Craftsmanship (Expertease Podcast #4)</title>
      <link>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/11/29/podcast-building-engineering-career-nikhil-prasad.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad (Part1) - Empowered Engineering Culture - Episode #3 In Part 1 of our conversation with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, we discussed ways &amp;amp; means of building an empowered Engineering culture, and how Mastery, Autonomy and Purpose play a key role in building a vibrant company culture. You can listen to the insighful conversation here: Nikhil Prasad - Part 1 - Engineering culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Empowered Engineering Culture - Nikhil Prasad (Expertease Podcast #3)</title>
      <link>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/10/02/podcast-empowered-engineers-nikhil-prasad.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Nikhil Prasad - Cultivating an Empowered Engineering Culture (Part1) In this third episode of Expertease, we have an insightful chat with Nikhil Prasad, CTO and co-founder of tavisca, a 700 people, product company, that is considered to be a strong people-centric organisation in Pune.
  Nikhil Prasad   Nikhil talks about&amp;hellip;
&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;If the why is ambitious &amp;amp; empowering, then it adds Purpose to the mission.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exiting the Rat Race -  The Entrepreneurial Journey of Sandeep Nanu (Expertease Podcast #2)</title>
      <link>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/08/01/podcast-exiting-the-rat-race-sandeep-nanu.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Sandeep Nanu - Exiting the Rat Race In this second episode of Expertease, we have a spirited chat with Sandeep Nanu, serial entrepreneur and founder of a brand and communication consulting firm WriteClick.
  Sandeep Nanu   Sandeep talks about his first job as a WebDesigner and the lessons he learnt there, including the important of respecting your commitments to other and their time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art of Experience Design with Aditya Karle (Expertease Podcast #1)</title>
      <link>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/07/22/podcast-art-of-experience-design.html/</guid>
      <description>Listen On: Spotify, Anchor.fm, Apple, Google Podcasts
 Description In this first episode of Expertease, we have a light-hearted chat with Aditya Karle, Head of Design at ThoughtWorks India, to deconstruct the art of Experience Design (XD).
  Aditya Karle   1:10: We talk about his journey to becoming a Designer and getting involved in Software Design, discuss differences between UI design, UX and XD.
28:50: We have an interesting chat about applying design thinking to Bengaluru International Airport.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10 reasons for buying the Ford EcoSport Petrol (Automatic) - Review</title>
      <link>/2019/12/30/ford-ecosport-automatic.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2019 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/12/30/ford-ecosport-automatic.html/</guid>
      <description>I spent a few months researching automatic petrol vehicles in India, before finally settling on the Ford EcoSport. Read on to find out why.
  Ford EcoSport   Disclaimer: Car specifications and quality are always changing. Please contact respective brands and companies for current specifications. This blog is based on my research to purchase a good petrol automatic vehicle for my needs, and I do not take any liability on the accuracy of the information mentioned here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
