<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on life-lessons.in</title>
    <link>/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on life-lessons.in</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Gurpreet Luthra 2021</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Indian Food Recipes App built with GlideApps [NoCode]</title>
      <link>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2021/06/19/29-indian-food-recipes-app-nocode/</guid>
      <description>Free App with over 100&amp;#43; Indian recipes Food Recipes App - NoCode My brother (Simarpreet), who is a home-chef, wanted to create a mobile app with Indian food recipes (mostly as made in Punjabi homes). The idea being that one has an app in their pocket that can be pulled out while doing grocery shopping, or standing in the kitchen, to quickly see simple home made recipes &amp;amp; ingredients.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bahmni - Open Source EMR with 1 Million Lines of Code</title>
      <link>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2021/02/25/30-bahmni-1million-loc/</guid>
      <description>Image courtsey: Friends without borders Bahmni Codebase - Moving out of AngularJS Bahmni, an open source hospital management system and EMR has over 1 Million lines of code (LoC)! Out of that over 164,000 LoC are in AngularJS (Angular 1.x). AngularJS is going to be end-of-life in Dec-2021, with no likely SLAs around fixes after Dec-2021.&#xA;In this article, I would like to shed some light into what parts of Bahmni depend on AngularJS, what parts are already in React; and suggest some steps forward to remove dependence on AngularJS.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Open Source Software</title>
      <link>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2017/03/12/open-source-explained/</guid>
      <description>My acoustic guitar - Greg Bennett I have been contributing to Open Source Software (OSS) for over 3 years now, at ThoughtWorks. Many people seem to have some misconceptions about OSS, or don’t fully realise the implications and impact of OSS. In this blog, I have shared a few of my learnings and thoughts on this topic. If you are technologist – who has some familiarity with OSS, then it’s likely that this article will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduce Computer Eye Strain with F.lux</title>
      <link>/2016/09/05/reduce-eye-strain-with-flux/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2016/09/05/reduce-eye-strain-with-flux/</guid>
      <description>About 3 years ago, one of my colleagues in ThoughtWorks, Sam Gibson, suggested I try out f.lux.&#xA;f.lux changes the Color temperature of my mac screen in the evening, so that the blue light from the screen is removed, and instead a nice warm set of colors are emitted from the screen. This drastically reduced the strain that I felt on my screen at night. It felt weird, the first 3 or 4 days, when my screen colors changed in the evening.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mars Rover Problem in Scala</title>
      <link>/2016/04/24/mars-rover-problem-in-scala/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2016 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2016/04/24/mars-rover-problem-in-scala/</guid>
      <description>Priyank Gupta, a respected ex-ThoughtWorker from the Pune office, wrote an excellent blog series in 2014 titled: Decoding ThoughtWorks Coding Problems.&#xA;In this blog he explains what constitutes good code &amp;amp; design, using the now decommissioned Mars Rover problem as an example. His code is in Java. I decided to showcase the same design in Scala, using only &amp;ldquo;the good parts&amp;rdquo; of Scala, with an aim of keeping the solution easy to understand, and enhance.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Vagrant Boxes and VMs</title>
      <link>/2015/10/03/understanding-vagrant-boxes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/10/03/understanding-vagrant-boxes/</guid>
      <description>On top of Mt Billing in Dharamshala, India Vagrant does a lot of things auto-magically under the hoods, and most of the times people are left confused when they want to delete or add boxes or VMs. I will try and explain the relationships between Base Boxes, VMs, Virtual Box Instances among other things, in this post.&#xA;Vagrant is an awesome tool for developers to get their own sandboxed environments to play with.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server on a Digital Ocean Droplet</title>
      <link>/2015/08/16/gocd-on-digital-ocean/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/08/16/gocd-on-digital-ocean/</guid>
      <description>Near Chinatown street in Singapore Today I experimented with installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server and agent on a Digital Ocean CentOS droplet. Note that you will need to ensure that you setup swap space on your digital ocean droplet, before proceeding with installing GoCD.&#xA;Read the steps here on my old blog: Installing ThoughtWorks GoCD Server and Agent on Digital Ocean Droplet.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Applications for Multiple Countries and Languages</title>
      <link>/2015/02/14/building-apps-for-multiple-countries/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2015/02/14/building-apps-for-multiple-countries/</guid>
      <description>Near Chinatown street in Singapore I have worked on a couple of projects where we had to make the application multi-country savvy (also called internationalisation or i18n), and I think it would be good to pen down various areas we considered, and the tools we used. Note that, these practices are from the perspective of a Java/Scala project, but can easily be adapted to other platforms too &amp;ndash; since the basic requirements are similar.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Way To A New Project</title>
      <link>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2014/11/28/way-to-a-new-project/</guid>
      <description>On top of Mt Billing in Dharamshala, India You move to a new project. Its exciting. It holds promise of something awesome (usually). You are ready to dive. You want to learn things fast. You want to contribute. You want to become effective. You want to be welcomed. And then maybe, become invaluable.&#xA;There are some tips I have learnt on how to navigate new projects effectively. I would look forward to hearing what you have to say about yours.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Difference between sorted, sortWith and sortBy in Scala</title>
      <link>/2014/07/26/scala-diff-between-sort-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2014/07/26/scala-diff-between-sort-methods/</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India Scala collections provide you three options for sorting: sorted(), sortWith() and sortBy(). Here is a simplified explanation:&#xA;sorted Will sort the list using the natural ordering (based on the implicit Ordering passed)&#xA;sortBy (an attribute) Sort by a given attribute using the attribute&amp;rsquo;s type. e.g. given a list of Person objects, if you want to sort them in ascending order of their age (which is an Int), you could simply say:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Capybara and Rspec assertions in Page Objects</title>
      <link>/2014/01/10/using-capybara-and-rspec/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2014/01/10/using-capybara-and-rspec/</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India On my Rails project, I am using RSpec and Capybara to write functional tests.&#xA;I did not want to specify any HTML elements in my Capybara feature files, since that makes the feature files brittle to HTML / CSS changes. It also violates the DRY principle and basic code hygiene.&#xA;Read the full blog on my older blog site here: Using Capybara and Rspec assertions in Page Objects</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vagrant: Setup development environments FAST!</title>
      <link>/2012/12/16/vagrant-an-interesting-approach-dev/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/12/16/vagrant-an-interesting-approach-dev/</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India If you have never heard of Vagrant, or are interested in understanding what is Vagrant, then this blog should be useful to you.&#xA;Setting up a development environment for many projects now-a-days isn&amp;rsquo;t a matter of simply running a script or downloading a piece of software. On most projects, the average setup time to get all up and running is usually a day, and sometimes more.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Reading for Lateral Dev Hires at ThoughtWorks</title>
      <link>/2012/07/29/recommended-reading-for-devs-thoughtworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/07/29/recommended-reading-for-devs-thoughtworks/</guid>
      <description>ThoughtWorks Tech Radar - Times Square Quite often experienced folks joining ThoughtWorks have a common set of questions: What should I read to prepare myself for ThoughtWorks? What kind of technologies does ThoughtWorks work on? Will I go on a Ruby or Java or Mobile project?&#xA;I doubt there is any good and precise answer to these questions. But, there certainly are some practices that I feel our in the DNA of ThoughtWorks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>POKA YOKE - Applying Mistake Proofing to Software</title>
      <link>/2012/07/22/poke-yoke-mistake-proofing-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/07/22/poke-yoke-mistake-proofing-software/</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India Note: This has been one of my highest read blog posts ever with over 100,000 views. I am humbled. Thank you!&#xA;For years, automobile companies have utilized &amp;ldquo;Mistake Proofing&amp;rdquo; as a technique for ensuring high quality, high speed manufacturing &amp;ndash; especially in cases of mass scale production. This is also known as Poka-Yoke (in Japanese) and was adopted and formalized as part of the Toyota Production System.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Web Vulnerabilities - Phishing, Cookies, XSS and CSRF</title>
      <link>/2012/04/29/understanding-web-vulnerabilities-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 02:13:50 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2012/04/29/understanding-web-vulnerabilities-cookies/</guid>
      <description>Near the Norbulingka Institute, Dharamshala, India Last week I gave a presentation on &amp;ldquo;Web Application Vulnerabilities&amp;rdquo; as part of our weekly Dev meetup at ThoughtWorks. The presentation was aimed at covering some vulnerabilities and risks that plague Web based applications, and to make folks aware of risks and possible mitigation options. In specific, topics covered were Phishing, Social Engineering, Cookies and Cross Site Request Forgery (CSRF or XSRF).&#xA;As a continuation to the presentation, I felt that writing a blog on it would crystallize the information I had collected and make it available to a larger audience.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
